whereas crete creator quality assurance
your job
i really think you screwed the pooch on
this one creed because of you
the entire company is in jeopardy we
have a crisis apparently a disgruntled
employee at the papermill decided that
it would be funny to put an obscene
watermark on our 24 pound cream letter
stock 500 boxes has gone out with the
image of a beloved cartoon duck
performing unspeakable acts upon a
certain cartoon mouse but a lot of
people like every week i'm supposed to
take four hours into a quality spot
check at the paper mill and of course
the one year i blow it off this happens
yes hello creed bratton quality
assurance dunder mifflin scranton i was
supposed to meet with one of your floor
managers last week for a quality
inspection and he or she wasn't there
and i'm trying to remember who it was
who wasn't there last week debbie brown
and which day was that wednesday the
11th perfect the only difference between
me and a homeless man is his job i will
do whatever it takes to survive like i
did when i was a homeless man when i
went over wednesday for the spot check i
got a call from debbie brown saying she
has an emergency dentist appointment
emergency dentist appointment now i'm
told she told her manager she had the
flu i'm a trusting guy but i just wish
debbie brown had been there we had a
contest got a farewell card for debbie
brown and you like to sign it
couple of bucks and i force you get some
children i feel terrible about debbie
brown she got fired because of dwight so
i thought i'd pass around a goodbye card
maybe everyone could put in a couple of
bucks to help her through these
difficult times why do bad things always
happen to the good people it's tragic
it's just tragic
[music]